i'm delighted to be part of this a great
meeting
the first of its kind i believe in kenya
and perhaps in africa and from the
response we are getting from across the
world perhaps
also in the world church and politics
i'm sure many have wondered why we
should hold
a whole three days summit
on the church and politics
throughout the history of the church
there has existed
attention among some christians
that the church and politics
needs to be separated
we need to separate ourselves from the
affairs of the world
especially from politics the picture
that has been painted is based on the
age-old adage that
politics is dirty and so
because christians are supposed to be
righteous
you should be as far as possible
from politics many christians therefore
view
those getting into politics as plunging
themselves into a dangerous world
of evil and the habits of corruption
likewise many churches have made it
their written or
unwritten policy never to engage
with political affairs they maintain
a deaf ear and a blind eye to all
matters to do with politics
but is politics that bad
the dictionary defines politics as the
art and science of government
or the art of influencing policy
or winning control this means that
at its best politics is about
using our spheres of influence
to accomplish goals for the common good
of the people yet one of the strongest
arguments against the church engagement
with politics
is that jesus never involved himself
in politics so why should we
i agree that in the narrow sense of the
definition of the word politics
jesus never engaged himself
in politics jesus never formed
a political party he never
adopted a political program or
organized any political protest
but in the broader sense of the world of
politics
jesus whole ministry was political
at the very onset of his ministry jesus
declared
the kingdom of god is at hand
kingdom talks about
politics leadership
a kingdom is headed by a king
and that talks about governance and
politics
and jesus said he had come to bring
about
a kingdom and in this he inaugurated
a new social order whose values and
standards
challenged the old fallen nature of man
and way of governance his teachings
were a stinging indictment to the evil
status quo
of his time therefore both the religious
and the political elite found him
offensively
radical they eventually killed him
because of it bearing the ultimate
consequence of the brute side
of politics that actually keeps us away
from this engagement but the implication
therefore is that
if the church is committed to the cause
of christ
and to the kingdom of god we cannot
afford to ignore political
engagement
2013 elections
the catholic bishop said
politics is too important for our
country
for us not to engage
and to keep silent and indeed it is true
politics is one
item and factor of any nation
that determines the progress
growth development or even demise
of nations jones thought in his book
issues facing christians today argues
that
and i quote no single word captures
more accurately or expresses more
eloquently
the modern sense of impotence than the
word
alienation alienation
he says is a cry of men and women
who feel themselves to be the victims of
blind
economic forces beyond their control
it is the frustration of ordinary people
excluded from the processes of decision
making
end of court what stock seems to be
saying is that
when the affairs of the nation are left
unguided
by the principles of the kingdom of god
then ordinary men and women shall
inevitably suffer alienation
oppress the weak the rich
exploit the poor the majority
of iran the minority
therefore starts assess that christians
cannot afford to be contaminated
by the spirit of alienation instead
christians must engage society and
influence it for the good of all
unfortunately when we look at our world
today the spirit of alienation
is everywhere men women
and children from all walks of life
are crying and groaning under the
oppressive powers of the privileged few
consequently people cry out for a savior
an instrument of god who can speak or
act
on their behalf to deliver them from
their sufferings
truth be told that instrument
of god is the church
it's that responsibility the people
groan so why has the church
not fully played its role
and what can we do to change
that situation
we are going to be trying to answer
during this summit
but let me briefly
explain some three areas that i believe
we need to consider as we begin our
discussion
and our conversation during this summit
because my role is to paint the picture
of our current scenario in kenya
and indeed in the rest of the world
though my counterpart on this particular
topic
will be coming in the afternoon to tell
us about
the broader global perspective
for us to be able to engage
politics as a christian community
the first thing i need i i think we need
to consider is
the mandate that we have received
what is our mandate has given to us
by god
received right from creation
god had a clear agenda for his creation
and especially for the human race
as the epitome of god's creation
god made human beings
as the stewards of the rest of his
creation
unfortunately with the fall of man
came sin and evil and all of god's good
plans
almost came to a note but you know that
god's plans cannot be thwarted and so he
came with a redemption plan
a way in which to put things together
until this world as we know it
comes to a close but in rebellion
human beings have constantly and
consistently
sought to live outside of the authority
of god
and unfortunately like fish out of water
we simply cannot survive
outside of god and no matter how much
we as human beings have tried to live
without
god we wiggle
around for a while in toil some labor
we gas for breath unlike
fish out of water we eventually
die in utter frustration
that is why in every generation god has
called a few individuals and given them
the mandate
to draw people back to the order
that he had put in place
scripture is that god in his sovereignty
super returns over the affairs
of every nation the bible tells us in
psalm
24 verse 1 the earth
is the lord's and everything in it
the world and all who live
in it sometimes it's a christian
community we think that
god is only concerned about church
we imagine that god operates only within
the confines of our four walls or six
worlds
or how many whatever number of walls you
have
around your sanctuary and so we imagine
that
god is contained in our sanctuaries
god is contained in the places of our
worship
the psalmist declares that god
is beyond our sanctuaries
god is beyond all that we see and
do god is beyond the church
the earth is the lord's
and the everything that is in it
and all who live in it
and that all means all
right now we are about seven billion
people on the first surface of this
earth
all those people belong to god
all those people are gods
whether they know it or not whether they
appreciate it or not
whether they acknowledge him or not
these people belong to god
it is for this reason therefore that god
every so often appointed individuals to
bring his special
message sometimes judgment to the
leaders
whenever they went away astray from
god's
ways
except for one such man to talk about
the mandate
that we have received jeremiah
is known to many of us jeremiah was
primarily called to speak to the people
of judah
and warned them of the impending
judgment
that was due to come upon them because
of their
going away from the purposes of god
worshiping idols and leaving
the place of god
but like most of us today jeremiah was
very reluctant to take up
this awesome responsibility and argued
and reasoned
with god but god would not let him go
in jeremiah chapter number 1
verse 17-19 god told him
get yourself ready stand up
and say to them whatever i command you
do not be terrified by them or
i will terrify you before them
god then assure them in verse 18 today
i have made you a fortified city
an iron pillar and a bronze wall
to stand against the whole land
against the kings of judah against its
officials
against its priests and against
the people of the land he wants jeremiah
in verse 19
they will fight against you but will not
overcome you for i am with you
and will rescue you declares
the lord
jeremiah was called to speak against the
ills
of his time he was to speak
to the kings he was to speak to the
officials
he was to speak to the priests he was to
speak
to the people of the land
jeremiah was called by god to bring
god's word to the political arena
god's word to the social scene
jeremiah was called by god to bring
god's word to the religious community
god's word
to all the people of the nation
and i want to say this is the same call
this is the same mandate that god has
given
his people who are called by his name
in his article empowered leadership
calvin miller points out that for
politics to have
a positive impact it must be conducted
with deference with courtesy
with public relations in order to get
people to grant you the power to lead
them
unfortunately in our context politics
seems to be
more of an art of manipulation
and eventual exploitation
who will bring the voice of god
into the political arena who will bring
the voice of god
into the social order who will bring the
voice of god
to the religious community who will
bring
the voice of god to the people
of the world if it is not we
who are called by his name if it is not
you and i who call ourselves
christians
of power within the political arena
happens
the people of god have the divine
mandate
to raise up a prophetic voice and bring
the
unequivocal word of god to the nation
to its peoples and to its leaders
whether they are politicians whether
they are religious
whether they are societal all these
people
are god's people are under his mandate
and he has given and delegated that
responsibility
to us as his people
the second
mandate that you have been given is to
bring a transformative
agenda to be salt and light
jesus told his disciples in matthew
chapter 5 verse 13 and 14
you are the salt of the earth
you are the light of the world
the implication here is that as
followers of jesus christ
we carry the singular responsibility
of ensuring that the society does not
decay
and that darkness does not overwhelm
our land this is our responsibility
that we cannot run away from jesus said
when
salt loses its saltiness it is of
no use but to be trampled upon
and if you are a keen observer
you may have noticed that the salt
in our society has at some point
lost his saltiness and the only thing
that the people do
is to trample upon that salt
all kinds of strong words against the
church
people call us names people don't take
us seriously as christians
why because we have lost
our saltiness
yesterday i was in a slightly
embarrassing situation
our leaders was introduced to me
that is our church member
church member
sitting there looked at me and said
bishop
at earlier
members should look like you
members should conduct themselves like
you
members
i thought
themselves like me and he looked down
and shook his head
and said you need more work
stress is saltiness it is of no use
but to be trampled upon
jesus said when the light is put in a
bushel
people sit in darkness
this is a responsibility that god
has given us the question is therefore
have god's people lived up to this dual
mandate
of being prophets and being
transformers this brings me to my second
point
the journey we have worked allow me to
very very briefly outline some things
that
men and women of god have done in the
period of history
in every period of history god
has used men and women to bring about
transformation
and change in society according to his
will and his purposes
moses delivered israel from the yoke of
slavery
in egypt david delivered
israel from an embarrassing encounter
with the philistine giant goliath
nehemiah restored the broken walls
of jerusalem elijah ashamed and killed
the prophets of baal
in the battle for supremacy of the gods
nathan rebuked david
when he abused his power in the new
testament
god picked peter to establish his charge
among the jews
he picked paul to take the gospel beyond
the borders of israel
at another level john the baptist
rebuked herod when he took his brother's
wife
and stephen spoke boldly against the
religious leaders
in contemporary history when the gospel
had become
a mere legalistic ritual god raised up
martin luther
to restore its message of grace his
namesake dr martin luther king jr
was later to be used of god to fight
against
racial segregation in the united states
of america
in fact the whole fight against slavery
was fought and won
by various christian men and women among
those at the forefront
of the struggle against apartheid in
south africa
was none other than archbishop that
montutu
here in our own nation the so-called
second liberation
was initiated by men and women of god
like bishop okulu bishop muge and
picked up later by act bishop dingman
zeke
bishop guitary reverend timothy joya and
many others who stood out from the crowd
and stood for the purposes of god
in the midst of darkness in the midst of
decay
they recognized that this is our mandate
that has been given
and they stood for it during the
constitutional review process
god raised up a small band of courageous
men and women
under the banner of the kenya church who
stood for the purposes of god
and significantly influenced content
of the final document
clear is that as we look at history
every significant and lasting change
in any nation or society has been
spearheaded
by individual christian men and women
or by the church in general
notwithstanding today we are at a place
where everybody looks back with
nostalgia
to the charge of yesterday
how many of us had people where are the
oculus
where are the mughals where are the soul
and souls
how did we get to this place
brings me to my third and last point
the rain that beat us
[Music]
honest with ourselves we have to accept
that the church
of today is a far cry
of what is expected we have not only
lost
our influence in society but we have
engaged in activities
that totally undermine our prophetic
call
and transformation agenda
it is a total contradiction that in a
nation that prides
itself to be 80 percent christian
we should also be 80 percent corrupt
the question that arises is where did
the rain
start beating us
[Music]
claim to have done any in-depth study on
that question
a casual observation brings to mind
several factors
that may have served to undermine the
prophetic voice
and the transformation agenda of the
church especially in the field
of politics and governance let me share
about a few as i started listing things
these things the list was growing longer
and longer and longer so i picked only
four
not in any order of significance
but factors that i believe have
served to undermine our prophetic voice
in the nation the first
is a discordant voice
distinctives of the prophets of old was
the unity of their message
for example jeremiah was a contemporary
of zephaniah of habakkuk of daniel
and of ezekiel when you read their
prophecies
though they had different focus the
message
was the same in the new testament
the gospel writers equally reflect a
unity
of message because these people spoke as
the spirit
led them the biggest challenge we face
today
is that our prophecies are sometimes so
discontent
as to be embarrassing
how can two men of god prophesy over two
presidential candidates
that the lord has said thou shalt surely
win
which lord is speaking
which prophet shall we believe
it puts us in a bad state because
the people who are observing and the
people who are
listening wonder which prophet
then do we believe because this one is
anointing with oil
the other one is anointing with oil all
are saying
the lord has said you are the one
there that god hates
as a person who proposed to speak on his
behalf
when he has not sent him
in the old testament such people were
stoned
to death if that law was to be
practiced today i don't know how many
would be sitting in this room this
morning
and how many would be listening online
voice has caused us to lose
our credibility
is a tribal bondage
the key characteristic of men and women
of old
was that they stood for god and not for
their races or tribes
they understood that in christ there is
neither jew
nor gentile neither male nor female
and no such divisions stood before them
whether you look at the historical
biblical historical prophets
whether you look at the global prophets
whether you look at our
own country here in kenya the men and
women of
all who stood and spoke spoke from the
word of god
not from their tribes
today is deeply racial
and largely tribal when it comes to
politics
we stand unashamedly with our people
it totally undermines our witness
i wonder how come that
all the people from one region
christians
somehow hear god telling them vote for
your man
from the same area seem to hear the
voice of god telling them this is the
man
how come brothers and sisters that we
are so
tribally bound that we cannot lose
ourselves
it undermines our voice
number three a love for money
one time prophet elijah held
healed a wealthy and powerful government
official
from his leprosy naman was
so grateful to god
that he offered elisha a thank you gift
the man of god refused to take it
because he thought the man of god was
unwise
and so he followed naman and took the
gift
when elijah found out he pronounced
naman's
leprosy upon our poor brother
gehaze brothers and sisters
if there is anything that is putting
political leprosy
upon the servants of god it is naman's
money
we cannot be courageous prophets
when we have taken naman's gifts
oh that no dog can bark
with a bone in its mouth and so they
come with a bone
the voice of the prophet muted
because of the gifts that the church
receives if we are going to rise up
and be the true prophets in this country
and in our world
we must refuse the gifts
of naman
number four and finally not because
these are the only four
as i told you i had a long list but like
the writer to the hebrews say
time does not permit
is a lack of wisdom
prophetic ministry is a dangerous job
requires great wisdom jesus told his
disciples
in matthew chapter 10 verse 16
behold i send you a ship
in the midst of wolves therefore be as
wise as serpents and as harmless
as doves
needed to address very similar
situations separately
over several hundred years apart
nathan was called by god to go and
confront king david
after he took somebody's wife
baptist fell compelled and prompted to
confront
king herod for also taking somebody's
wife
with a great story to david and how the
king pronounced
judgment upon himself
rebuke and had his head chopped off
[Music]
whereas prophetic ministry requires
courage
and courage that we must not shy away
from it also calls
for wisdom unfortunately
many times we as christian leaders and
christians in general
have lacked wisdom on how
to confront ills in our society
many of us have acted or spoken in ways
that totally
undermine the purposes of god
and no wonder sometimes our microphones
are muted
no wonder sometimes our heads are
chopped off
[Music]
these are but a few factors that i
believe have been part of the rain
that beat us however
let me borrow from the politicians even
though we have rain
been rained on
and yeshua
don't see a lion rained on and imagine
that it is a cut it is just a matter of
time hallelujah
and the mans are going to dry up
and we are going to rise again because
we are part of the lion of the tribe of
judah
who has conquered when nobody could open
the seal
jesus was found to be the only one
who could conquer and he said i am
building my church
and the gates of hell shall not prevail
against it and so we may look like we
are down like we have been reigned on
and it may look like the world is
overcoming us
but brothers and sisters jesus is not
about to allow his church to be
conquered
jesus is not allowed about to allow his
church
to be overrun jesus is not about to
allow the guests of hell
to prevail against his church the church
moves on
samsung was a powerful man he was
captured by the philistines
who shaved his hair of strength and then
turned
him into a play thing at their
amphitheater
but samson's hair began to grow
brothers and sisters fellow servants of
god
in this summit we are going to be
brutally honest with one another and
with ourselves
but our prayer is that god will allow
our hair to grow
and like samsung we are not going to
pray that we die
we are going to live to see the
salvation of the lord in the land of the
living
we want to avail ourselves to be used of
god
to bring about change that we urgently
need
and we desperately look for
and so i want to invite all of us
to listen carefully to the voice of god
to hear what god may be saying
you may be here as a church leader you
may be here as a
a an ordinary christian in the
marketplace
you may be here as a student you may be
here in whatever capacity
you are a politician god is speaking to
us today
he wants to raise up an army that will
take
this land for the kingdom of god
god bless you